Guide to the Elizabeth Burtner papers, 1903-2003 MS2150
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Dancers and trends in dance, 1903-2003; MS2150 Series 2; 7 Linear feet (Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 3)
  - Dancers--Erdman, Jean, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Dancers--Falco, Louis, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Dancers--Fonteyn, Margot, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Dancers--Goslar, Lotte, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, 1930-1949 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, 1950-1958 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, 1960-1968 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, 1970-1989 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, 1990-2002 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    Text on photograph: "U.S. Department of State Magazine Reprint Unit, IPS-IIA WP-52 MR-53-S-95 All Dance Is Contemporary Martha Graham, one of the foremost dancers in the United States, is shown here in the role of Emily Dickinson in "Letter to the World," which she created some years ago and revived in April 1952. Miss Graham in discussing her work says that all dancing is contemporary and that freedom of thought for the individual is necessary in the creative arts. Miss Graham's discussion of the dance is of particular interest since she has created a number of new dance roles and has established a system of teaching dance which has been copied widely. (50-2722)"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    Text on photograph: "U.S. Department of State Periodicals Service Unit, IPS-IIA MR-R-140 Martha Graham: Outstanding American Choreographer 1. The American dancer and choreographer Martha Graham, considered the greatest in her profession, has played a leading role in the evolution of modern dance."
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    Text on photograph: "U.S. Department of State, Periodicals Service Unit, IIA-IPS MR-R-133 America's Outstanding Choreographers Compared (2 Parts) 1. Martha Graham, American choreographer and outstanding exponent of modern dance, features herself as a soloist in dances that veer from comic parodies to those expressive of neurotic fears and deep, obsessive terrors. (Photograph courtesy of George Platt Tynes)"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Text on photograph: "U.S. Department of State Periodicals Service Unit, IPS-IIA MR-R-140 Martha Graham: Outstanding American Choreographer 3. In her creation "Punch and Judy", the outstanding American dancer and choreographer Martha Graham introduced superb satire to the realm of modern dance. Considered the finest in her profession, her originality and inventivemenss have made it possible for her to develop a new medium of communication."
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
    Text on photograph: "#S-1 - Ethel Winter, Bertram Ross, Phyllis Gutellius in SERAPHIC DIALOGUE Music: Dello Joio Set: Isamu Noguchi Choreography: Martha Graham"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Text on photograph: "#G-7 - Yuriko and Bertram Ross in EMBATTLED GARDEN Music: Carlos Surinach Set: Isamu Noguchi Choreography: Martha Graham"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
    Text on photograph:"#G-6 - Robert Cohan, Yuriko and Bertram Ross in EMBATTLE GARDEN Music: Carlos Surinach Set: Isamu Noguchi Choreography: Martha Graham"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
    Text on photograph: "#AG-2 - ACROBATS OF GOD - David Wood and Helen McGehee Music: Carlos Surinach Sets: Isamu Noguchi Choreography: Martha Graham"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
    Text on photograph: "#AG-8 - ACROBATS OF GOD - Robert Powell, Martha Graham and David Wood Music: Carlos Surinach Sets: Isamu Noguchi Choreography: Martha Graham"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
    Text on photograph: "#AG-9 - ACROBATS OF GOD - Robert Powell, David Wood and Martha Graham. Music: Carlos Surinach Sets: Isamu Noguchi Choreography: Martha Graham"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
    Text on photograph: "#C-1 - Mary Hinkson and Robert Powell in CIRCE. Music: Alan Hovhaness. Set: Isamu Noguchi. Choreography: Martha Graham.
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
    Text on photograph: "#C-2 - Mary Hinkson with Peter Randazzo, Robert Powell, Clive Thompson and Bertram Ross in CIRCE. Music: Alan Hovhaness. Set: Isamu Noguchi. Choreography: Martha Graham."
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
    Text on photograph: "#PR-2 - Members of the Martha Graham Dance Company in PART REAL - PART DREAM Music: Mordecai Seter Set: Dani Karavan Choreography: Martha Graham"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    Text on photograph: "#PR-3 - Mary Hinkson in PART REAL - PART DREAM Music: Mordecai Seter Set: Dani Karavan Choreography: Martha Graham"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    Text on photograph: "Martha Graham and Company: action photographs by Martha Swope from the book MARTHA GRAHAM: PORTRAIT OF THE LADY AS AN ARTISTS, text by LeRoy Leatherman, to be published by Knopf on October 24, 1966."
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
    Text on photograph: "#J-5 - Martha Graham in LEGEND OF JUDITH Music: Modecai Seter Choreography: Martha Graham Set: Dani Karavan"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
    Text on photograph: "#J-6 - LEGEND OF JUDITH - Martha Graham. Music: Mordecai Seter Choreography: Martha Graham Set: Dani Karavan"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, 10/11/1966 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    Text on photograph: "Performance, Oct. 10 and 11, 1966. Martha Graham and Dance Co, Lisner, GW Univ Reception, Dimock Gallery, Oct 11th. Martha Graham entering the Gallery; Elizabeth Burtner, head of dance, GW Univ, on her right."
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, 10/11/1966 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    Text on photograph: "Performance, Oct. 10 an 11, 1966. Martha Graham and Dance Co., Lisner Reception, Dimock Gallery 10/11/66"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, 10/11/1966 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    Text on photograph: "Performances Oct. 10 and 11. Martha Graham and Dance Co. Lisner GW Reception, Dimock Gallery 10/11/66"
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, 10/11/1966 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    Text on photograph: "Performance, Oct. 10 and 11, 1966. Martha Graham and Dance Co, Lisner, GW Univ. Reception, Oct 11, Dimock Gallery. from L to R: Evelyn Davis, Dance Playhouse Wash DC; Dorothy Looker, TV WTOP; an affiliate of Institute of Contemporary Arts; Martha Graham; Dr. Hamblin, Dean of the School of Education, GWUn."
  - Dancers--Graham, Martha, 1966 (Flat box 8, Folder 5)
  - Dancers--Halprin, Ann, 1967-1972 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Dancers--Halprin, Ann, undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
    Text on photograph: "Dancers Workshop Co. 321 Divisadero St., San Francisco, Cal. 94117"
  - Dancers--Halprin, Ann, undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
    Text on photograph: "photo Peter Moore"
  - Dancers--Hanna, Judith Lynne, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Dancers--The Rebekah Harkness Foundation, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Dancers--Hawkins, Eric, 1959-1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Dancers--Henry Street Playhouse, 1957-1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Dancers--Hill, Martha, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Dancers--Holder, Geoffrey, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Dancers--Holm, Hanya, 1941-1956 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Dancers--Horst, Louis, 1936-1964 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Dancers--Howing, Louis, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Dancers--Humphrey, Doris, 1941-1995 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Dancers--Humphrey-Weidmen Dance Company, 1935-1942 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Dancers--Humphrey-Weidman Dance Company, 1935 ca. --1936 ca. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Text on photograph: "Charles Weidman and Group in "With My Red Fires" 1935-36 New Dance Trilogy - Theatre Piece; With My Red Fires; New Dance - premiered successively in Bennington College and New York. Choreography, Doris Humphrey"
  - Dancers--Humphrey-Weidman Dance Company, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Text on photograph: "U. S. Information Agency Magazine Reprints, IPS WP-275 MR-55-S-41 Doris Humphrey: Yesterday and Today 1. One of the group of young dancers who evolved a personal dance language in the 1920's and 1930's, Doris Humphrey is shown here in a movement study taken when the Humphrey-Weidman Compnay was in residence at Mills College in California. Of her work Miss Humphrey has said, 'I wish my dance to reflect some experience of my own in relationship to the outside world; to be based on reality illumined by imagination ... and to make its contribution toward the drama of life.' (55-872)"
  - Dancers--Humphrey-Weidman Dance Company, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Text on photograph: "U. S. Information Agency, Magazine Reprints, IPS WF-275 MR-55-S-41 Doris Humphrey: Yesterday and Today 2. Gaiety is the prevailing mood of 'Exhibition Piece, ' created by Doris Humphrey in 1931. Here she is shown with Charles Weidman, left andJose Limon in one of the movements of that dance. Miss Humphrey has an impressive list of compositions to her credit. She was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1949 to write a book on choreography and in 1953 received the Capezie Dance Awared for her creative leadership in the modern dance. (55-873)"
  - Dancers--Humphrey-Weidman Dance Company, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
    Text on photograph: "U.S. Department of State, Periodicals Service Unit IIA-IPS MR-R-136 America's Outstanding Choreographers Compared ( 2 Parts) 2. Doris Humphrey, American choreographer and outstanding exponent of modern dance, is a thoughtful craftsman who can direct others and teach them to portray the meaning of her work -- which is largely in the affirmative. (Photograph courtesy of New York Herald Tribune)"
  - Dancers--Johnson, Raymond, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Dancers--Jones, Betty, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Dancers--Jones, Betty True, 1964-1968 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Dancers--Jones, Betty True, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    Text on photograph: "Betty True Jones in the Kathakali Dance Drama 'Putana Moksham'"
  - Dancers--Jones, Betty True, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    Text on photograph: "Betty True Jones in Kathakali Dance Drama and in Mohiniyattam"
  - Dancers--Jones, Betty True, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
    Text on photograph: "Betty True Jones in Kathakali Dance Drama"
  - Dancers--Jones, Betty True, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Dancers--Jones, Bill T., 1999 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Dancers--King, Eleanor, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Dancers--Kitchall, Ina, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Dancers--Koner, Pauline, 1955-1966 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Dancers--Koner, Pauline, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
    Text on photograph: "Pauline Koner"
  - Dancers--Koner, Pauline, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
    Text on photograph: "Pauline Koner 'Cassandra'"
  - Dancers--Kurath, Gertrude P., 1931-1983 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Dancers--Kriegsman, Sali Ann, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Dancers--Lamhut, Phyllis, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Dancers--Lewitzky, Bella, 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Dancers--Limon, Jose, 1947-1969 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Dancers--Limon, Jose, 1970-1999 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Dancers--Limon, Jose, undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
    Text on photograph: "Jose Limon"
  - Dancers--Limon, Jose, undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Dancers--Limon, Jose, undated (Flat box 8, Folder 6)
  - Dancers-Limon,Jose, undated (Flat box 8, Folder 7)
  - Dancers--Louis, Murray, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Dancers--Lutz, Katherine, 1951-1959 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Dancers--Maslow, Sophie, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Dancers--McKayle, Donald, undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Dancers--LaMeri, undated (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Dancers--DeMille, Agnes, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Dancers--Mitchell, Arthur, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Dancers--Nagrin, Daniel, 1958-1972 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Dancers--Nagrin, Daniel, undated (Box 6, Folder 45)
    Text on photograph: "Daniel Nagrin, 36 W 73 St, NYC 23 NY"
  - Dancers--Nikolais, Alwin, 1956-1971 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Dancers--Perez, Rudy, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Dancers--Rudy Perez Dance Theater press release, 04/21/1970; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Dancers--Pilobolus, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Dancers--Pomare, Eleo, undated (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Dancers--Primus, Pearl, 1950-1966 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Dancers--Rainer, Yvonne, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Dancers--Robbins, Jerome, 1957-1972 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Dancers--Rodgers, Rod, 1966-1972 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Dancers--Rosenthal, Jean, 1963-1969 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Dancers--Sanasardo, Paul, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Dancers--Shawn, Ted, 1954-1968 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Dancers--Shearer, Sybil, 1946-1969 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Dancers--Sokolow, Anna, 1967-1970 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Dancers--St. Denis, Ruth, 1941-1968 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Dancers--Tamaris, Helen, 1952-1960 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Dancers--Taylor, Paul, 1962-1989 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Dancers--Taylor, Paul, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    Text on photograph: "Paul Taylor"
  - Dancers--Taylor, Paul, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 63)
    Text on photograph: "Paul Taylor and Co."
  - Dancers--Taylor, Paul, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Dancers--Taylor, Paul, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Dancers--Taylor, Paul, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Dancers--Taylor, Paul, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    Text on photograph: "Paul Taylor and (partner) Co."
  - Dancers--Taylor, Paul, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Dancers--Paul Taylor Dance Company flyer, 04/28/1970-04/29/1970; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Dancers--Tetley, Glen, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Dancers--Tharp, Twyla, 1965-2003 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Dancers--Thimley, Erika, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Dancers--Weidman, Charles, 1936-1969 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Dancers--Weidman, Charles, 1970-1993 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Dancers--Weidman, Charles, 1970 ca. --1979 ca. (Box 6, Folder 74)
    Text on photograph: "C. Weidman 1970's"
  - Dancers--Weidman, Charles, 1970 ca. --1979 ca. (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Dancers--Weidman, Charles, 1970 ca. --1979 ca. (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Dancers--Weidman, Charles, 1970 ca. --1979 ca. (Box 6, Folder 77)
    Text on photograph: "To Elizabeth -- With great [illegible] Charles"
  - Dancers--Weidman, Charles, undated (Box 6, Folder 78)
    Text on photograph: "To Betsy [illegible] Charles" "Charles Weidman was noted for his use of a drum (Wigman drum) in leading groups in presenting modern dance type of techniques. See clipping of group of students (high school) St. Louis. Photo from Charles Weidman Betsy Burtner"
  - Dancers--Weidman, Charles, 1970 ca. --1979 ca. (Box 6, Folder 79)
    Text on photograph: "To Betsy Love from Charles" "Charles Weidman 1970's"
  - Dancers--Wigman, Mary, 1931-1967 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Dancers--Wilson, Anne, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Dancers--Winter, Ethel, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Dancers--Yuriko, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Oral history, Elizabeth Burtner, 09/30/1979; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    General
    Transcript (partial) of oral history interview with Elizabeth Burtner conducted by Miss. Theresa Bowers for the Columbia University Oral History Research office. The interview was conducted in the Holiday Inn in Washington, D.C.,on September 30, 1979. The interview is one of a series documenting the Bennington Summer School of the Dance. The portion in this file appears to be a copy with corrections possibly by Ms. Burtner.
  - Programs, 1950-1976 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Programs, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Square dance night at building J dance studio, photograph, circa 1940-circa 1959; Series 2 (Flat box 8, Folder 9)